Guide to the Moses Coit Tyler collection, 1779-1900 (bulk 1850-1900)
Tyler, Moses Coit collection, 1779-1900 (bulk 1850-1900)
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Moses Coit Tyler collection, 1779-1900 (bulk 1850-1900)
14-17-2641
Tyler, Moses Coit,
9.5 linear ft.
Diaries, letters, manuscripts.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Diaries, lecture notes, and commonplace books by Moses Coit Tyler, and letters to him from others.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
American scholar, Congregationalist minister from 1859-1862, professor of English 1867-1881 at University of Michigan, then the first professor of American history, at Cornell University from 1881-1900. Pioneered in the scholarly study of American literature; helped to found the American Historical Association in 1884.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Correspondence, diaries, manuscripts, clippings, and documents by, to or about Moses Coit Tyler, richly documenting his personal and family life, his religious and scholarly pursuits, and the reception of his scholarly work. Includes correspondence among many members of Tyler's family, ranging in date from 1779-1899; drafts of sermons, lectures, and speeches Tyler gave, including an 1871 speech, "Woman is a Person"; diaries Tyler kept from 1858-1859 and 1870-1899; manuscripts (mainly letters) of prominent Americans; and commonplace books in which Tyler recorded quotations, kept from 1853-1855 and 1857-1861. Also included are reviews of and personal letters about Tyler's books A History of American Literature During the Colonial Time, 1607-1765; The Literary History of the American Revolution, 1763-1783; Patrick Henry; Three Men of Letters; and Glimpses of England. Correspondence includes letters from Tyler to his wife Jeannette in which he records his and other people's reactions to the events of the Civil War.
Correspondents include Charles Kendall Adams, J.B. Angell, M.D. Conway, Willard Fiske, S.S. Harris, Paul Hamilton Hayne, G.H. Putnam, H.W. Sage, Jacob Gould Schurman, Edmund Clarence Stedman, T. Tilton, and A.D. White. Family correspondents include Roland Greene, Mary Greene Tyler, Charles C. Tyler, John Tyler, Elisha Tyler, Olive Tyler, Rebecca Tyler, and Jeannette Tyler. Manuscripts collected by Tyler include letters by John Trumbull, Nathaniel Niles, and William Wirt Henry, with 2 letters by Daniel Webster and an autograph essay by Abbé Raynal, "Nouvelle Angleterre."
SUBJECTS
Names:
Tyler, Moses Coit, 1835-1900.; Adams, Charles Kendall, 1835-1902.; Angell, James Burrill, 1829-1916.; Conway, Moncure Daniel, 1832-1907.; Fiske, Willard, 1831-1904.; Greene, Roland.; Harris, Samuel, 1841-1888.; Hayne, Paul Hamilton, 1830-1886.; Henry, Patrick, 1736-1799.; Henry, William Wirt.; Niles, Nathaniel, 1741-1828.; Putnam, George Haven, 1844-1930.; Raynal, (Guillaume-Thomas-François), abbé 1713-1796.; Sage, Henry W. (Henry Williams), 1814-1897.; Schurman, Jacob Gould, 1854-1942.; Stedman, Edmund Clarence, 1833-1908.; Trumbull, John.; Tyler family.; Tyler, Charles C.; Tyler, Elisha.; Tyler, Jeannette.; Tyler, John.; Tyler, Mary Greene, 1807-1894.; Tyler, Moses Coit, 1835-1900.; Tyler, Moses Coit, 1835-1900.; Tyler, Moses Coit, 1835-1900.; Tyler, Moses Coit, 1835-1900.; Tyler, Moses Coit, 1835-1900.; Tyler, Olive, 1772-1840.; Tyler, Rebecca Coit, 1810-1836.; Webster, Daniel, 1782-1852.; White, Andrew Dickson, 1832-1918.; Congregational Church -- Sermons.
Subjects:
American literature -- Study and teaching.; American literature -- History and criticism.; Women's rights -- United States.; Historians -- United States.; Literary historians -- United States.
Places:
United States -- History -- Study and teaching.; United States -- Intellectual life -- 19th century.; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865 -- Personal narratives.
Form and Genre Terms:
Diaries.; Commonplace books.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
NOTES
Most of the correspondence and reviews, and all of the manuscripts Tyler collected, are bound in scrapbooks; diaries and lecture notes are also bound.
COLLECTION ARRANGEMENT
Organized into the following series: Diaries; Tyler family papers, 1779-1843; notes for a genealogy of the Tyler family; lecture notes and commonplace books; letters to Tyler; manuscripts collected by Tyler; family letters by Tyler, 1854-1899; reviews and letters concerning books by Tyler; sermons; documents and undated manuscripts; clippings; unbound letters.
Diaries and correspondence arranged in chronological order.
SERIES LIST
Series I. Diaries
Series II. Letters
Series III. Lecture and course notes and commonplace books
Series IV. Family papers and genealogy
Series V. Clippings
CONTAINER LIST
- Series I. Diaries
  - Diary, 1858 (Volume Bd. Ms. 12 tiny)
  - Diary, 1859 (Volume Bd. Ms. 13 tiny)
  - Diary, 1859 (Volume Bd. Ms. 63 tiny)
  - Diary (mainly on visit to England; one entry at end written in Ann Arbor, Michigan), November 2, 1864-November 14, 1866; March 1, 1870 (Volume Bd. Ms. 64 tiny)
  - Diary, 1870 (Volume Bd. Ms. 14)
  - Diary (cover title "Memorandum book"), December 1870-January 1871 (Volume Bd. Ms. 65)
  - Diary, 1871 (Volume Bd. Ms. 15 tiny)
  - Diary, 1872 (Volume Bd. Ms. 16 tiny)
  - Diary, 1873 (Volume Bd. Ms. 17)
  - Diary, 1874 (Volume Bd. Ms. 18++)
  - Diary, 1875 (Volume Bd. Ms. 19++)
  - Diary, 1876 (Volume Bd. Ms. 20)
  - Diary, 1877-1880 (Volume Bd. Ms. 21)
  - Diary, March-December 1881 (Volume Bd. Ms. 22)
  - Diary, 1859 (Volume Bd. Ms. 13 tiny)
  - Diary, 1882 (Volume Bd. Ms. 23)
  - Diary, 1883 (Volume Bd. Ms. 24)
  - Diary, January-November 1884 (Volume Bd. Ms. 25)
  - Diary, November-December 1884 (Volume Bd. Ms. 26)
  - Diary, 1885 (Volume Bd. Ms. 27)
  - Diary, 1886 (Volume Bd. Ms. 28)
  - Diary, 1887 (Volume Bd. Ms. 29)
  - Diary, January 9-June 6, 1888 (Volume Bd. Ms. 31 tiny)
  - Diary, June 7-July 23, 1888 (Volume Bd. Ms. 30 tiny)
  - Diary, July 23-October 10, 1888 (Volume Bd. Ms. 32)
  - Diary, 1888 (Volume Bd. Ms. 33 tiny)
  - Diary, January 1-July 30, 1889 (Volume Bd. Ms. 34)
  - Diary, November 1889-May 1890 (Volume Bd. Ms. 35 tiny)
  - Diary, May 15, 1890-November 13, 1893 (Volume Bd. Ms. 36 tiny)
  - Diary, December 1, 1893-April 20, 1898 (Volume Bd. Ms. 37 tiny)
  - Diary (trip to England), July 1-August 18, 1897 (Volume Bd. Ms. 38 tiny)
  - Diary (trip to Quebec and the White Mountains), August 1898 (Volume Bd. Ms. 39 tiny)
  - Diary (trip to Europe), March-September 1899 (Volume Bd. Ms. 40 tiny)
- Series II. Letters
  - Index to Moses Coit Tyler correspondence (photocopy), 1854-1900 (Volume Bd. Ms. 48++)
  - Incoming correspondence, v. 1, 1854-1866 (Volume Bd. Ms. 50++)
  - Incoming correspondence, v. 2, 1867-1876 (Volume Bd. Ms. 51++)
  - Incoming correspondence, v. 3, 1867-1872 [sic] (Volume Bd. Ms. 52++)
  - Incoming correspondence, v. 4, 1873-1876 (Volume Bd. Ms. 53++)
  - Outgoing correspondence (manuscript copies of letters), December 1874-1878 (Volume Bd. Ms. 11+)
  - Incoming correspondence, v. 5, 1877-1881 (Volume Bd. Ms. 54++)
  - Letters pertaining to Tyler's History of American Literature During the Colonial Time, 1878-1897 (Volume Bd. Ms. 1+)
  - Incoming correspondence, v. 6, 1881-1885 (Volume Bd. Ms. 55++)
  - Incoming correspondence, v. 7, 1886-1889 (Volume Bd. Ms. 56++)
  - Incoming correspondence, v. 8, 1890-1897 (Volume Bd. Ms. 57++)
  - Incoming correspondence, v. 9, 1898-1900 (Volume Bd. Ms. 58++)
  - Incoming correspondence on Tyler's Literary History of the American Revolution, 1897 (Volume Bd. Ms. 59++)
  - Manuscripts collected by Tyler (mainly letters), circa 1768-1898 (Volume Bd. Ms. 61++)
  - Outgoing family correspondence, 1854-1899 (Volume Bd. Ms. 62++)
  - Miscellaneous (letters, portraits, documents), circa 1879-1897 (Volume Bd. Ms. 66++)
  - Incoming correspondence on Tyler's Patrick Henry, 1887-1897 (Volume Bd. Ms. 68++)
- Series III. Lecture and course notes and commonplace books
  - Commonplace book, 1853-1855 (Volume Bd. Ms. 3)
  - Student course notes and commonplace book, Yale Theological Seminary, 1857-1858 (Volume Bd. Ms. 4+)
  - Student course notes and commonplace book, Yale Theological Seminary, 1857-1858 (Volume Bd. Ms. 4+)
  - Student course notes, Andover and Yale, 1857-1858 (Volume Bd. Ms. 49+)
  - Student course notes and commonplace book, Andover, 1858-1862 (Volume Bd. Ms. 5+)
  - Commonplace book, 1864-1869 (Volume Bd. Ms. 6)
  - Commonplace book (and notes on reading), 1867-1869 (Volume Bd. Ms. 7++)
  - Commonplace book, 1868-1881 (Volume Bd. Ms. 8++)
  - Commonplace book, 1869-1879, 1890 (Volume Bd. Ms. 9++)
  - Commonplace book, 1871-1881 (Volume Bd. Ms. 10)
  - Notes for Tyler's lecture "The Early Colleges and College-Builders of America", undated (Volume Bd. Ms. 41)
  - Notes for Tyler's lecture "The Old English Ballads", undated (Volume Bd. Ms. 67 tiny)
- Series IV. Family papers and genealogy
  - Tyler family papers, 1779-1842 (Volume Bd. Ms. 44++)
  - Tyler family papers, 1843-1899 (Volume Bd. Ms. 45++)
  - Notes for genealogy, 1856-1900 (Volume Bd. Ms. 46++)
- Series V. Clippings
  - Clippings (cover title "Personal records"), 1853-1875 (Volume Bd. Ms. 42)
  - Reviews of American Literature During the Colonial Time, 1878-1897 (Volume Bd. Ms. 2++)
  - Clippings, 1879-1897 (Volume Bd. Ms. 43+)
  - Reviews of The Literary History of the American Revolution, 1897-1898 (Volume Bd. Ms. 60++)
  - Reviews of Tyler's Patrick Henry, 1887-1888 (Volume Bd. Ms. 69++)
  - Reviews of Tyler's Three Men of Letters and Glimpses of England, 1895-1898 (Volume Bd. Ms. 70++)